RG 028:006, Committee on the Structure of State Government (Filer Committee), 1975-1977
Connecticut State Library
Committee on the Structure of State Government records
1976-1977
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Committee on the Structure of State Government
15 cubic feet
The Committee studied the overall functions of state government and its agencies as well as their relationships with commissions and committees.
RG028_006
1977-001
Historical Note
In November 1975, Gov. Grasso asked John H. Filer, Chairman of Aetna Life and Casualty, to serve as chairman of a committee to "study the overall functions of state government and its agencies as well as their relationships with commissions and committees." Other members, appointed early in December, were James Wade, Hartford lawyer; Ruth Sims, of the League of Women Voters; and James Fesler, Professor of Political Science at Yale. A small staff, headed by Harold Hovey, had offices in the Aetna building. The Committee was supported by private and business contributions.
The Committee, which had been requested to make its recommendations by the end of 1976, held its first meeting on December 18, 1975, and met thereafter once or twice a month. The staff first conducted a survey or "inventory" of the existing state agencies and commissions, and requested opinions and comment from their heads. Studies were made of the government structure of other states, and the reports of previous similar committees in Connecticut were examined.
A "discussion draft" incorporating the Committee's preliminary views was published in October 1976, followed by a strenuous effort to publicize it widely, to explain it to the people and the legislature, and to solicit comments and criticisms on it. Several public hearings were held.
The final report titled, "Better organization for better government," was submitted to Gov. Grasso on December 20, 1976. Its recommendations were succinctly described and the proposed new structure was outlined in some detail. In essence, it suggested the consolidation of some 210 agencies and commissions into fifteen major departments, plus an expanded Office of the Governor and a new Office of Policy and Management.
Holding the view that earlier reorganization efforts had fallen short because of failure to press hard enough for implementation, Mr. Filer and the Committee and staff members continued active efforts to sell their program to the public and the legislature. Public interest and support were stimulated through the efforts of a separate group of private and business people calling themselves Citizens for Better Government Through Reorganization. Draft legislation was prepared for the General Assembly and testimony was given before the Government Operations and Policy Committee. After a number of amendments were made, the major bill, S.S.B. 357, was passed by both houses in May and signed by the Governor on June 2, 1977 (P.A. 77-614, separately published as Vol. III of Public and Special Acts, January Session, 1977).
Scope and Content
Includes reoprts, meeting records, inventory of state agencies and commissions, correspondence, press clippings, public ocmment, research office files, report drafts, an implementation file, hearing and conference tapes, legislation material, and reference files.
Related Material
RG 028:001, Commission to Investigate the Advisability of Consolidating Certain State Boards and Commissions and to Investigate the Public Health Laws, 1915.
RG 028:002, Commission on the Reorganization of State Departments, 1935-1937.
RG 028:003, Commission to study the Integration of the State Judicial System, 1943-1945.
RG 028:004, Commission on State Government Organization, 1949-1950.
RG 028:005, Commission on Services and Expenditures (Etherington Commission), 1971.
RG 028:007, Human Servuces Reorganization Commission, 1977-1979.
RG 028:008, Governor's Study Group on Limitation on Expenditures, 1978-1979.
RG 028:009, Commission to Study the Management of State Government (Thomas Commission), 1989-1991.
RG 028:010, Commission to Effect Government Reorganisation (Hull-Harper Commission), 1991-1992.
Index Terms
Persons:
Fesler, James; Filer, John H; Hovey, Harold; Sims, Ruth; Wade, James
Organizations:
Connecticut. Committee on the Structure of State Government
Subjects:
Administrative agencies -- Connecticut; Connecticut. Committee on the Structure of State Government -- Records and correspondence; Connecticut -- Politics and government -- 1951-; Executive departments -- Connecticut; State governments -- Connecticut
Document Types:
Agendas (administrative records); Audiocassettes; Bills (legislative records); Clippings; Correspondence; Minutes; Press releases; Reports
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
The State Archives accessioned these records in June 1977.
Container List
- Records, 1976-1977
  - Reports, 1976 (Box 1)
    Published reports of the Committee.
    - Progress report by Chairman John Filer, 1976 June 10; 4 pages (Box 1)
    - Better organization for better government, 1976 october; 190 pages (Box 1)
      Preliminary discussion draft. Also included are an earlier version, dated September 1976 (187 pages), and "Chapter Summaries," dated October, 1976 (16 pages).
    - Better organization for better government, 1976 December 20; 65 pages (Box 1)
      Final report.
    - Better organization for better government: Summary, 1976 December 20; 12 pages (Box 1)
  - 2. Meeting records, 1975 December-1976 December; 10 inches (Box 1)
    Agenda, minutes of meetings, working papers prepared for consideration, and related notes and correspondence. Also includes graphics of charts for meetings of February 19 and March 29, 1976.
    Chronological.
  - 3. Inventory of state agencies and commissions, 1976 March-1977 April; 1 foot (Box 2)
    Form reports, based on interviews with heads of agencies, and related notes and correspondence. The reports contain brief data on enabling citation, key staff, number of employees, budge and non-state funding sources, functions, etc. Some related material resulting from the Committee's title, followed byu a binder containing photocopies of form reports.
  - 4. Correspondence, 1976 March-1977 May; 1.5 inches (Box 2)
    A small file, probably from the Research Director's desk, with letters to and from Committee members (Filer, Sims, Fesler), and staff principals (Hovey, Olsen, McLean, Nagle).
  - 5. Press clippings, 1976-1977; 8 inches (Box 3)
    Clippings of press stories about the discussion draft, the final report, the reorganization bill, and public reaction to them.
    Largely unarranged.
  - 6. Public comment, 1976; 5 inches (Box 3)
    Letters and transcripts of hearing statements by members of the public and organization representatives concerning the Committee proposals.
    Alphabetical by name.
    Much similar material is in the Research office files.
  - 7. Research office files, 1976-1977; 3.5 feet (Box 4-6)
    These materials came from the offices of Thomas Cosgrove, Research Director, and Eunice Groark, Assistant Research Director. They include correpondence, memoranda, notes, preliminary studies, drafts, reference materials, etc., pertaining to all aspects of the Committee's work. In the first box are some subject-labeled files, fund-raising records, and administrative materials.
    Largley unarranged, unfiled, unprocessed.
  - 8. Report drafts, 1976; 1 foot (Box 7)
    Original drafts, related notes, edited copy for final versions, etc.
    Unarranged.
  - 9. Implementation file, 1976 May-1977 March; 9 inches (Box 8)
    Correspondence, memoranda, press releases, draft testimony and other material pertaining to the effort to achieve public support and legislative action on Committee recommendations. Includes papaers of a "public relations advisory committee" and of the Citizens for Better Government.
    Arranged by subject but otherwise unarranged.
  - 10. Hearing and conference tapes, 1976 October-1977 April; 14 cassettes, 2 tapes (3 inches) (Box 8)
    Cassettee tapes of hearings in Fairfield, Groton, Hartford, Meriden and Torrington and tapes of the Conference on Reorganization, Hartford, April 13, 1977.
  - 11. Legislation material, 1976-1977; 6 feet (Box 9)
    Publications and related materials (mostly printed) pertaining to the structure, organization an dowrk of Connecticut agencies, commissions and committees. Included are annual reports, organization charts, public relations material, etc.
    Arranged alphabetically by agency.
    - Adult probation (Box 10)
    - Agriculture (Box 10)
    - Arbitration (Box 10)
    - Arts (Box 10)
    - Auditors (Box 10)
    - Civil Air Patrol (Box 10)
    - Civil Preparedness (Box 10)
    - Commerce (Box 10)
    - Consumer protection (Box 10)
    - Correction (including Justice Academy) (Box 10)
    - Dental Commission (Box 10)
    - Education (Box 10)
    - Education (Box 10)
    - Elections Commission (Box 11)
    - Engineers and Land Surveyors Board (Box 11)
    - Environmental protection (Box 11)
    - Finance and control (Box 11)
    - Fire arms (Box 11)
    - Fire protection (Box 11)
    - Handicapped (Box 11)
    - Health (Box 11)
    - Higher Education (Box 11-12)
    - Historical Commission (Box 12)
    - Housing (Box 12)
    - Human rights (Box 12)
    - Human services (Box 12-13)
    - Intergovernmental programs (Box 13)
    - Labor (Box 13)
    - Liquor COntrol (Box 13)
    - Mental health and Mental retardation (Box 13)
    - Motor vehicles (Box 13)
    - Personnel (Box 13)
    - Pharmacy (Box 10)
    - Planning and energy policy (Box 13)
    - Public utilities (Box 14)
    - Recreation (Box 14)
    - Resources recovery (Box 14)
    - Safety (Box 14)
    - State Library (Box 14)
    - State Police (Box 14)
    - Tax (Box 14)
    - Transportation (Box 15)
    - Treasurer (Box 15)
    - Veterans' hospital (Box 15)
    - General and miscellaneous (Box 15)